Lorenzo Fontolan, PhD Computational Neuroscientist

lorenzo.fontolan@gmail.com | https://fontolanl.github.io/lfontolan | +1-571-376-8253

JANELIA RESEARCH CAMPUS - 19700 Helix Dr, Ashburn, VA 20147

Summary

I am a Computational Neuroscientist with a background in Physics and significant experience in mathematical and computational modeling, machine learning, problem solving and data analysis. Currently I am a research scientist in the lab of Dr. Sandro Romani where, in collaboration with the experimental lab of Dr. Karel Svoboda, I investigated the brain mechanisms behind decision-making and motor preparation. I am interested in understanding the neural basis and the evolution of intelligent behavior in animals and humans, hoping that a better understanding of ourselves will lead to a more compassionate and just society.

Skills

Programming Skills: Python, Matlab, C, XPP

Other: Dynamical Systems, Neuroscience, Statistics, Machine Learning, Statistical Physics, Neural networks, Theano, Tensorflow.

Janelia Research Campus – HHMI | Research Scientist [October 2021-present]

Janelia Research Campus – HHMI | Research Associate [2015 – September 2021]

- Built computational models of short-term memory, challenged long-standing hypotheses on the role of slow neural timescales during decision-making, and established a causal link between the persistent firing of cortical neurons and short-term memory (published in Nature)
- Trained artificial neural networks to reveal how information is transmitted between brain areas.
 Uncovered the neural mechanisms that allow short-term memories to persist and repel incoming interferences (published in Nature Neuroscience)

I presented my work at several leading conferences in the Neuroscience field (Sfn, Cosyne, HHMI) and organized introductory courses to Computational Neuroscience at Janelia Research Campus.

Research experience

ENS Paris – University of Geneva | PhD in Neuroscience [2011 – 2015]

- Developed and tested a state-of-the-art **biophysical model** of speech perception in cortical circuits
- Analyzed brain recordings from human patients. Combining both the modelling and the data analysis
 approaches enabled us to identify the role of brain rhythms in speech perception.
- Carried out the mathematical analysis of a simplified spiking neuron model

Published in: Nature Communications, eLife, Trends in Neuroscience and Journal of Mathematical Neuroscience.

Center for Theoretical Neuroscience – Columbia University | Exchange student [2009 – 2010]

Employed computational and mathematical tools to study how to efficiently store and retrieve correlated
memories in Hopfield networks (M.Sc. thesis work: "Learning of hierarchical memories with binary
synapses")

PhD in Neuroscience (2011 - 2015, University of Geneva)

Advisors: Prof. Anne-Lise Giraud and Prof. Boris Gutkin - Graduation Mark: 6/6

M. Sc. in Physics (2008-2011, La Sapienza University of Rome)

Education

Concentration: Dynamical systems and statistical physics. Advisors: Prof. Stefano Fusi (Columbia University of New York), Prof. Enzo Marinari - Graduation Mark: 110/110 cum laude

B. Sc. in Physics (2004-2007, La Sapienza University of Rome)

Concentration: Condensed matter physics. Graduation Mark: 109/110

Google scholar page: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=01jqJYoAAAAJ&hl=en h-index = 7, i-index = 7

- 1. Neural algorithms and circuits for motor planning. Annu. Rev. Neurosci. (in press)
- 2. Attractor dynamics gate cortical information flow during decision-making. Nat. Neurosci. (2021)
- 3. Discrete attractor dynamics underlying selective persistent activity. Nature (2019)

Publications

- **4.** Θ -band and β -band neural activity reflects independent syllable tracking and comprehension of time-compressed speech. **J. Neurosci.** (2018)
- 5. Neural cross-frequency coupling: from mechanism to function. Trends. Neurosci. (2015)
- 6. Speech encoding by coupled cortical theta and gamma oscillations. eLife (2015)
- **7.** The contribution of frequency-specific activity to hierarchical information processing in the human auditory cortex. **Nat. Commun.** (2014)
- 8. Analytical insights on theta-gamma coupled neural oscillators. J. Math. Neurosci. (2013)

Talks and awards

Talks and seminars: NYU, Brandeis U., U. of Oregon, Rice Univ., ENS Paris, U. of Marseille, IDIBAPS Barcelona, U. of Geneva, U. of Padova, NJIT, Sfn Annual Meeting Washington DC, ICMN France, Bernstein symposium

Best PhD thesis in Neuroscience, Amicitia Excellence Prize 2015 (10,000 CHF)

Toochine
Teaching,
mentoring &
academic
services

2021	Organizer, Bernstein symposium "Control mechanisms for contextual computations and behavior"					
2021	Mentor, Neuromatch academy 2021					
2020	Content Reviewer, Neuromatch academy 2020					
2019	Organizer and lecturer, Mathematical Methods for Neuroscience and ML @Janelia					
2019	Speaker, Venice Summer School in Computational and Theoretical Models in Neuroscience					
2017 – 2019	Lecturer, Introduction to Computational Neuroscience Undergraduate Seminar @Janelia					
2018	Invited Lecturer, General Philosophy course (Catholic University of America).					
2017	Attendee, Scientists Teaching Science course (NIH)					
2017	Co-creator, exhibition on AI and Neuroscience "WHAT? Machines that learn"					
2016	Attendee, Methods in computational neuroscience course, MBL, Woods Hole, MA.					
2015	Mentor and Thesis Supervisor, "Isomorphism of Hopfield nets and Ising model", B. Sc. in Physics,					
	La Sapienza University of Rome					
2006 – 2009	Tutor, college and high school physics and mathematics					
Reviewer for:	Nat. Neurosci., Neuron, PNAS, Plos Comp. Biol., Cortex, Commun. Biol., Comput. Biol. Med., Lang.,					
	Cogn. Neurosci., Neurons behav. data anal. theory					

Languages

Italian, English, French and Spanish.